Guide to the Robert Blum Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert Blum papers
1950-1964
MS 87
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.25
(6 boxes)
The papers consist of professional papers largely reflecting Robert Blum's activities with organizations working on problems in Asia and international affairs. Almost half of the papers are records of the Asia Foundation (1953-1962). Included are monthly reports, speeches and articles, and notes and photographs from annual trips to Asia (1953-1964). Other organizations represented include the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, UNESCO, the American Assembly, and the National Strategy Seminar.
Blum, Robert, 1911-1965
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dr. Isabelle Blum, 1969.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of Blum's professional papers, largely reflecting his activities with organizations working on problems in Asia and international affairs. Almost half of the papers are records of the Asia Foundation (1953-1962) during his presidency. Included are monthly reports, speeches and articles and notes and photographs from annual trips to Asia (1953-1964). Other organizations represented include the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, UNESCO, the American Assembly and the National Strategy Seminar.
General correspondence and expense vouchers are filed at the beginning of the papers. Following are papers arranged alphabetically by organization.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Blum, a specialist in Asian Affairs, was born in San Francisco on March 12, 1911. He spent his childhood in San Francisco and Japan (Yokohama and Kobe). He earned his undergraduate (A.B., 1930) and his graduate degree (Ph.D. 1936) from the University of California at Berkeley. From 1937 to 1942, he was a research assistant and instructor in international relations at Yale University. He served in the OSS from 1942 to 1946, spending most of those years in London. In the fall of 1944, he was named Chief of the X-2 Branch set up in Paris, one of the Branches of the Counter Espionage division of the OSS. After the war he worked for two years as an assistant to Secretary of Defense James Forrestal. In 1949, Robert Blum returned to Europe, working in Paris with the Marshall Plan. From 1950 to 1951, he was the head of ECA (Economic Cooperation Administration), an agency of the Marshall Plan, in Indochina. He returned to the United States in 1953 to become the President of the Asia Foundation with headquarters in San Francisco. He left the Asia Foundation in 1962 to direct a three-year project for the Council on Foreign Relations financed by the Ford Foundation titled "The United States and China in World Affairs". Robert Blum died suddenly on Long Island (N.Y.) on July 9, 1965 before he could revise his manuscript for publication. His book, The United States and China in World Affairs, edited by A. Doak Barnett, was published the following year.
Asia; Cambodia -- Description and travel; Cambodia -- Foreign relations -- United States; Laos -- Description and travel; Laos -- Foreign relations -- United States; Southeast Asia; United States -- Foreign relations -- Cambodia; United States -- Foreign relations -- Laos; United States -- Foreign relations -- Vietnam; United States -- Foreign relations; Vietnam -- Description and travel; Vietnam -- Foreign relations -- United States; Educators; Blum, Robert, 1911-1965; Asia Foundation; United States. Economic Cooperation Administration; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory, 1950-1964; 2.3' (6 boxes)
  - General correspondence, 1955-1956, 1959-1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Expense vouchers, 1954, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Assembly
    - Correspondence, 1956-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Reports, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Asia Foundation
    - Monthly reports, 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
    - Monthly reports, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 13-17)
    - Program bulletins, 1956-1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Trip notes
      - Vietnam, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Cambodia, Indonesia, Vietnam, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Afghanistan, Burma, Ceylon, India, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Japan, Korea, Singapore, Vietnam, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Afghanistan, Burma, Malaya/Singapore, Pakistan, Philippines, Thailand, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Cambodia, Ceylon, India, Indonesia, Laos, Vietnam, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Afghanistan, Hawaii, India, Japan, Korea, Laos, Malaya/Singapore, Pakistan, Thailand, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Cambodia, Ceylon, India, Japan, Okinawa, Philippines, Singapore, Taiwan, Vietnam, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Afghanistan, Burma, Hong Kong, Indonesia, Laos, Kuala Lumpur, Nepal, Pakistan, Thailand, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - India, Malaya, Singapore, Hong Kong, Taiwan, Japan, Kuala Lumpur, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Cambodia, Japan, Singapore, Kuala Lumpur, France, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Trip photographs
      - Laos, Vietnam, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Pakistan, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Ceylon, Philippines, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Japan, Korea, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Burma, Thailand, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Afghanistan, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Vietnam, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Afghanistan, Burma, Cambodia, Ceylon, Hong Kong, Japan, Korea, Laos, Malaya/Singapore, Pakistan, Philippines, Taiwan, Thailand, Vietnam, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Taiwan, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Speeches and notes, 1953-1965 (Box 3, Folder 39-41)
    - Articles by Robert Blum, 1956-1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - U.S. newspaper clippings, 1954-1956 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Foreign newspaper clippings, 1955-1962 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Asia Foundation. Working Group on Cultural and Educational Advancement in Asia
    - Correspondence, 196l March - December (Box 4, Folder 45-46)
    - Reports, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 47-48)
  - Association for Asia Studies
    - Report, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Bilderberg Group. Fredenberg Conference, 1956 May 11-13
    - Memoranda, reports, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Reports, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace
    - Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Economic Cooperation Administration
    - Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 53-54)
    - Clippings, 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Harvard University
    - Correspondence, 1957-1960 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - International House
    - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Mutual Security Agency
    - Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 58-59)
  - Pacific Coast Conference on the University and World Affairs, 1962 Mar 16-17
    - Correspondence, speech, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - UNESCO
    - Conference on Social Change in Southern Asia and the United States, 1956 Apr 23-27
      - Correspondence, memoranda, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Conference on Asian-Western Cultural Relations, 1956 Aug 13-14
      - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, 1955-1957 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Third Major Project, 1959
      - Correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - UNESCO. U.S. National Commission
    - Correspondence, reports, 1959-1962 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - U.S. Department of State. Consultancy on foreign aid
    - Correspondence, reports, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 65)